Guide to the Communist Collection of A.E. Forbes, 1921-1972 AIS.2000.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Communist Collection of A.E. Forbes
1921-1972
AIS.2000.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
4.6875 linear feet (3 boxes)
Adolph Edward Forbes was a member of the Communist Party (CP) in Pittsburgh from the late 1930s through World War II. The collection presents broadsides and newsletters, some of which were hand rendered and relate specifically to the region, others are widely available Communist Party and Left wing propaganda. The collection also contains family and wartime correspondence, fictional writing, and a diary. Digital reproductions of selected material is available online.
Forbes, A. Edward (Adolph Edward), 1907-
Biography
Born in 1907, Adolph Edward Forbes lived in the Oakland neighborhood of Pittsburgh with his mother, father, and siblings. Following high school, Forbes spent fifteen years working in Pittsburgh and also traveling throughout the country, both on his own and later with the United States Navy. By the early 1930s Forbes was a member of the Communist Party, as evidenced by his involvement with its front organizations such as the Workers International Relief (WIR), Cultural Division. Forbes' work in the CP reflected his own interests, such as writing, acting, and selling books. During this time, Forbes worked on novels and short stories. He also acted in local productions of radical plays, was involved in the Pittsburgh Pen and Hammer (a working-class literary publication), and tried to establish a labor research library. There is no indication that Forbes held any high post in the Communist Party at either the national or local level.
In 1940, Forbes left civilian life and entered the United States Navy. In the Navy, Forbes was first a clerk and later a shipbuilder. It was during this time that Forbes met his future wife, Shirley Levine. They were married during World War II and eventually settled in Pittsburgh. While Forbes briefly attended the University of Pittsburgh following high school, he completed his degree after the war, making use of the G.I. Bill. In the next decades, Forbes remained in Pittsburgh with his family and became active within the local Jewish community.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection has been broken down into two series. The first presents a collection of Left wing agitation and propaganda publications that demonstrate representative rhetoric on positions important to the American Left during the Depression decade through World War II. Primarily in the form of broadsides, pamphlets, newsletters, and flyers, these documents detail both issues known internationally and ones unique to Pittsburgh. For a sampling of material contained within this series, please consult the online exhibit at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/communist-collection-ae-forbes. Additional information on this series is found in the Series I scope note in the contents list located below.
Series II consists of material personal to Forbes, such as his writing and correspondence. The correspondence that Forbes maintained with his family and friends in the midst of his travels prior to World War II comprise the majority of this series. The collection contains letters as early as 1922, but not until the late 1920s is the correspondence continuous. Additionally, this series contains his efforts at writing fiction (drafts of short stories, ideas for novels, and scripts for plays) and a 1939 diary detailing his thoughts on life, women, and politics. While the focus of Series II is not communism or the Communist Party, documents and references to both are found throughout the series. Further information on Series II is provided in the contents list.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were acquired by the Archives Service Center in October 2000.
Previous Citation
Communist Collection of A.E. Forbes, 1921-1972, AIS.2000.07, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Forbes, A.E., Papers, ca. 1921-1972, ais 2000:07 as well as A.E Forbes Communist Collection.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/communist-collection-ae-forbes.
Communist Party of the United States of America.; Forbes family; Forbes, A. Edward (Adolph Edward), 1907-; Authors, American -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Communists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social action
- Left Wing and Labor Agitation Broadsides, 1925-1949; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Topics covered in Series I reflect the involvement of Left wing groups (notably the CP) in local, national, and international affairs. Locally, documentation includes hand-rendered, mimeographed broadsides pertaining to issues including strikes, rallies, and protests for imprisoned labor leaders such as Phil Frankenfeld and James Egan. Also documented are local efforts to aid hunger and advocate for unemployment benefits. Flyers demanding justice for Eugene Cole, an African-American from Pittsburgh jailed for alleged murder are included as well. Flyers, course descriptions, and events from the Pittsburgh Workers School also reside in Series I.
  At a national level, documents reveal Left wing participation in elections along with activism for unemployment and social security benefits. Items pertaining to Tom Mooney and the Scottsboro Boys are well represented. This series also reflects international circumstances such as the Communist Party's relationship with the Soviet Union, the rise of fascism, and the Spanish Civil War.
  Beyond broadsides, pamphlets, and flyers, there are several labor publications, often specific to a given factory or mill. Youth publications from both the Youth Communist League (YCL) and National Student League (NSL) are also included.
  The documents found in the first sixteen folders can be viewed at http://images.library.pitt.edu/a/aeforbes. The online exhibit displays a representative selection of this series.
  - Left Wing Pamphlets and Flyers, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - Flyers, Pamphlets, Newsletters, and Broadsides, 1930-1940 (Folder 10-14)
  - Pittsburgh Workers School, 1933-1939 (Folder 15-16)
  - Unemployed Councils and Pennsylvania Unemployed League, 1933-1937 (Folder 17-18)
  - International and National Affairs, 1932-1940 (Folder 19-20)
  - Youth and Student Movement, 1932-1940 (Folder 21-22)
  - Notices for Miscellaneous Economic Issues, 1932-1937 (Folder 23)
  - International Affairs, 1934-1939 (Folder 24)
  - The Workers International Relief Cultural Activities, 1932-1935 (Folder 25)
  - The American League Against War and Fascism, 1934-1939 (Folder 26)
  - Civil Rights and CP Youth Bulletins, 1935-1944 (Folder 27)
  - International and National Affairs, 1933-1939 (Folder 28)
  - Socialist Labor Party of America, 1925-1935 (Folder 29)
  - Western Pennsylvania Communist and Labor Publications, 1935-1939 (Folder 30)
  - Illinois and Indiana Labor Publications, 1933-1940 (Folder 31)
  - Labor Publications from Various States, 1933-1939 (Folder 32)
  - Bulletin of Events, Allegheny County, Educational Bulletin: International Labor Defense, 1935-1937 (Folder 33)
  - Left Wing Youth Publications, 1932-1936 (Folder 34)
  - The Bulletin of the United Committee of South Slavic Americans, 1946 (Folder 35)
  - Open Letters to Communist Party Members, 1934-1940 (Folder 36)
  - Political, Cultural, and Economic Publications, 1933-1942 (Folder 37)
  - Jewish Newsletter and Leaflets, Muldowney Political Photographs, 1930-1940 (Folder 38)
  - Issues of the Fight Against War and Fascism, 1936 (Folder 39)
  - Issues of PM Newsletter, 1930-1940 (Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous Labor and CP Flyers Calling for Racial Equality, 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Tom Mooney Letters, Posters, and Broadsides, 1933-1937 (Folder 2)
  - Left Wing Cultural Material, 1930-1938 (Folder 3)
  - CP Material Dealing with Race and Culture, 1934-1937 (Folder 4)
  - American Veterans Committee (AVC) Newsletters and Pamphlets, 1947-1948 (Folder 5)
  - Invitations and Bulletins to CP Events: Pre-War and Post-War, 1938-1946 (Folder 6)
  - Issues of InFact Newsletter, 1942-1950 (Folder 7-8)
  - Pen and Hammer Bulletin: Local and National, 1932-1935 (Folder 9)
  - Leaflets, Prints, Printed Letters, 1931-1945 (Folder 10)
  - The Pennsylvania Veteran, 1948 (Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous CP Items, 1932-1940 (Folder 12)
  - Agitation Theatre Written For Recruitment, 1937 (Folder 13)
- Writing and Correspondence, 1920-1962; II.
  This series contains the personal material of Forbes, including many items that do not explicitly relate to communism. Most prominently featured in this series are Forbes' correspondence with his family, friends, and people he met while away from Pittsburgh. More specifically, his sister Ethel and his friend Herbert Leifer account for most of the correspondence. Folders marked 'miscellaneous' usually refer to female acquaintances he met or one of the few cousins with whom he remained in contact. Beyond family and friends, Forbes also corresponds extensively with his fiancée, Shirley Levine. Letters to a war buddy, Heinz, reveal that Forbes was assigned to spy on subversives while stationed in Alaska with the Navy (Folder 18).
  Series II also displays Forbes' interest in writing short stories, novels, and plays. Although the series does not contain any completed works, it does include several outlines, drafts, and sketches for projects that Forbes intended on using to launch a writing career. In one instance Forbes worked on a novel about a female heroine, many of the files containing questionnaires and articles relate to this venture. In 1939, Forbes intermittently kept a diary in which he divulges information ranging from his concern with the direction of his life to his relationship with women and his political views.
  For researchers aiming to find Forbes' work with the Communist Party, there are a few documents that explicitly relate to this. A small notebook and several pages from a larger notebook provide meeting minutes from the Pittsburgh Pen and Hammer. Also, letters from the Workers International Relief express Forbes interest in doing 'cultural' work for the Party. In addition to these, the correspondence, while primarily focusing on the more mundane aspects of life, sometimes relates to the Communist Party and communism.
  - Miscellaneous Instructional Writing and Female Adolescent Material, 1937-1939 (Folder 14)
  - Questionnaire Dealing With Politics, Economics, and Sex, 1938-1939 (Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Advertisements and Forbes' Mother's Death Notice, 1948-1955 (Folder 16)
  - Forbes Family Material: Home, School, and Religion, 1958-1962 (Folder 17)
  - Post War Correspondence (Two Items), and, 1947 1949 (Folder 18)
  - Fictional Writing by A.E. Forbes, 1920-1940 (Folder 19)
  - Wartime Correspondence with Shirley Levine, 1944-1945 (Folder 20)
  - Wartime Correspondence with Immediate Family, 1941-1943 (Folder 21)
  - Letters Written by A.E. Forbes, 1922-1933 1945 (Folder 22-23)
  - Forbes Diary and Novel Notes, 1939 (Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous Letters to A.E. Forbes, 1922-1936 (Box 3, Folder 1-18)
  - Correspondence: Immediate Family, 1922-1936 (Folder 19-29)
  - Herbert Leifer to A.E. Forbes, 1926-1931 (Folder 30-34)
  - Miscellaneous Material Written by Forbes, 1929-1939 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - School Work and Paper, Undated (Folder 2)
  - Various Writings, 1936-1939 (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Marie Boyer, 1939 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Edna Pearl, 1940 (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Carol R., 1939-1940 (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Dolly, 1942-1943 (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Marian and Buzzie, 1939-1940 (Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Alice, 1941-1943 (Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Letter from Forbes, 1941-1943 (Folder 10)
  - Papers, Essays, and School/College Items, 1929-1939 (Folder 11)
  - Pictures and Letter, Undated (Folder 12)
  - Letters to County and State Officials, 1938 (Folder 13)
  - Maps: National and International, Undated (Folder 14)
  - Scripts: 'Out of the Sky,', 1937 (Folder 15)
  - Scripts: 'Two Worlds,', 1937 (Folder 16)
  - Popular Song Sheet, Undated (Folder 17)
  - Issue of New Masses (not complete), Undated (Folder 18)